# Leandro Bahia

Brazilian

Juiz de Fora - MG

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/leandrodbahia

I am currently a consultant, I support companies in the data area to build pipelines that generate value for the business

I work more effectively in data engineering, however, I also work with the business to understand their needs.

I build self service BI and also help with building visualizations in tools like Power BI
I have **7 years** of experience as a **Delphi developer** and **6 years** working as a **data consultant** 

Having a cool project, I'm available to talk!:)

#### FORMATIONS

2020 - 2022

2010 - 2011

#### Estácio de Sá

<u>Database</u>

#### IFET

• Computer Technician

# LANGUAGES

## **Portuguese**

Native

#### **English**

- Advanced (reading, writing, listening), intermediate (speaking)
- C1 Advanced (<a href="https://www.efset.org/cert/Q9yGMo">https://www.efset.org/cert/Q9yGMo</a>)

#### Spanish

• Intermediate (Reading, writing, speaking)

#### CERTIFICATE

#### 2022

#### Microsoft

- Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Fundamentals (DP-900)
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Fundamentals (AZ-900)

# **SCRUMstudy**

Scrum Fundamentals Certified (SFC)

# EXPERIENCES

#### 02/2024 - 2024

# Contractor Data Ops Enginner Senior (remote)

- Company: ABI (Ambev international)
- Project: Integrate business Jira ticket information into Databricks
- Description: Developed the entire integration with Jira for our Databricks workspace, consuming Jira issues in Python
- I modeled all the tables
- Developed the bronze (raw with JSON files), silver and gold layers
- Created all dimension and fact tables (star schema)
- Developed the Workflow in Databricks
- Helped answer business questions
- Supported and helped develop visions in Power BI
- Technologies: Azure, Databricks, Python, SQL, Spark, Jira, Power BI, GIT

# 12/2023 - 02/2024

# Contractor Senior Data Engineer (remote)

- Company: Westrock
- Project: Support of the HR Data Hub project for analytical information regarding the company's human resources universe at a global level
- Description: Maintained and developed new reports to answer business questions, for this I had to maintain existing flows and queries in addition to creating new ones
- Redesigned the DW layers (bronze, silver and gold)
- Technologies: Alteryx, SQL Server, Power BI

# 02/2023 - 12/2023

# Contractor Senior Data Engineer (remote)

- Company: Unimed BH
- Project: Migration from SSIS 2012 project to SSIS 2019
- Description: The Belo Horizonte unit updated its environment from SQL Server 2012 to SQL Server 2019, including a new server
- Configured the new server with all the prerequisites to support the packages developed in the 2012 version, migrating and adjusting them to work correctly in the 2019 version
- Technologies: SQL, SSIS, SQL Server, Oracle

# 10/2023 - 11/2023

# Contractor Senior Data Engineer (remote)

- Company: WestRock
- Project: Improved performance in Excel
- Description: The "three-bar unit" had a spreadsheet with horrible performance, simply navigating through the cells caused slowness.
- The spreadsheet logic was rebuilt using VBA, performing around 80% of the transformations there, including using a very interesting feature within Excel itsel called SQL Embedded to manipulate this information through lockups
- Technologies: Excel, VBA, SQL

# 09/2023 - 10/2023

### Contractor Senior Data Engineer (remote)

- Company: WestRock
- Project: PENF
- Description: Project made in Power Apps and Power Automate to request approval of order, approval and monitoring of invoices
- Technologies: Power Apps, Power Automate, SQL Server, Sharepoint

#### 08/2023 - 09/2023

# Contractor Senior Data Engineer (remote)

- Company: Mercantil do Brasil
- Project: Conduct Indicators
- Description: Due to regulation, it was necessary to automate a step in the internal process, a CSV file was manually exported from a system called

CRK, in Pyhon this file was automatically sent to S3, using Snowflake we created an external table that mirrored these CSV files, we used dbt to perform transformations on this external table, finally this final transformation was consumed by an SSIS

- We use DBT as an orchestrator and carried out the entire process from data consumption, treatment to the final generation to be consumed in Power BI
- Responsible for:
  - o Creation and management of the project schedule
  - o Technical leadership
  - o Data architecture and modeling in Snowflake
  - o Creation of information in the staging layer
  - o Creation of information in intermediate tables
  - Creation of fact and dimension tables
  - o Creation of queries and performance improvements
- Technologies: SQL, DBT, Snowflake, Power BI, Google Sheets

#### 01/2023 - 07/2023

## Contractor Senior Data Engineer (remote)

- Company: Mercantil do Brasil
- Project: Integration of brokerage products into the management base
- Description: Among several indicators, we mapped fraud
- Responsible for:
  - o Creation and management of the project schedule
  - Technical leadership
  - o Data architecture and modeling in Snowflake
  - o Creation of information in the staging layer
  - o Creation of information in intermediate tables
  - Creation of fact and dimension tables
  - o Creation of queries and performance improvements
  - o Building code in Pyhon to upload the file to \$3
  - Construction of the external table in Snowflake
- Technologies: SQL, Python, DBT, Snowflake, Google Sheets

# 12/2021 - 01/2023

# Senior Business Intelligence Analyst (remote, Pato Branco, PR - Brazil) – Viasoft

- Responsible for the analysis and development of the company's data warehouse (Oracle) and BI (PowerBI) integrating the internal system Viasell (Firebird), Korp (SQL Server/PostgreSQL), JIRA (API), SenseData (API) and Movidesk (API), Voors (API) e Google Sheets
- Responsible for gathering technical and requirements about the business needs, development and maintenance of the entire ETL layer (Pentaho), using the star model (Star Schema) of dimension and fact tables, later ingesting them in the data warehouse to create the analyzes and Dashboards in Power BI
- KPIs/dashboards were developed in Power BI so that analyzes and strategic decisions can be made about customers, such as new contracts, upgrade/downgrade of modules, upgrade/downgrade of users, terminations and GCC (churn combat)
- Performance and performance indicators were developed for employees who use the Jira and Movidesk tools, thus having daily monitoring of their indicators, they were updated via API for the Voors platform (corporate social network) and KPIs/ dashboards in Power BI
- Technologies: SQL, Power BI, SenseData (Sense Analytics), Pentaho Data Integration, Firebird, Oracle, DBeaver, SQL Developer, Java, JIRA, Postman, Jenkins, DBT, Google Sheets

# 08/2020 - 12/2021

## Senior Systems Analyst (remote, Pato Branco, PR - Brazil) – Viasoft

Requirements analysis, technical analysis

- Assistance to other developers and analysts
- Development of new features, in addition to bug fixes in the Agrotitan system (ERP)
- Responsible for adapting the ITS Bayer integration with the system referring to royalties from agricultural producers
- I adapted several integrations, especially related to inspection bodies of agricultural defenders, such as CREA (SP, Brazil) (text file), SIG@ (RS, Brazil) (text file), SIGEN (SC, Brazil) (web service) and SISDEV (MT, Brazil) (web service)
- I adapted our integration system with Bayer regarding LGPD (Brazil GDPR analoque)
- Technologies: SQL, Delphi 7, Delphi 10.1 Berlin, Firebird, IBExpert, Oracle, SQL Developer, JIRA, Postman, Jenkins

# 2019 - 2020

# Senior Systems Analyst (remote, São Paulo, SP - Brazil) – Servimex Logística

- Requirements analysis, technical analysis
- Assistance to other developers and analysts
- Development of new functionalities, in addition to bug fixes in the internal system of the company DDBroker (COMEX) in addition to maintaining some robots, which are responsible for capturing this information at the Federal Revenue Service to update internal information, either by consulting via web service or manipulating a webbrowser and getting the information by reading the page objects, either by an XML or XLS file or by consulting the PW3270 emulator through a DLL
- Technologies: SQL, Delphi 10.1 Berlin, SQL Server, SQL Server Management Studio, JIRA, Postman

#### 2018 - 2020

#### Contractor

- Requirements analysis, technical analysis
- Delphi development, consulting, specific demands and related issues

# 2015 - 2017

## Senior Systems Analyst (Juiz de Fora, MG - Brazil) – Thomson Reuters

- Requirements analysis, technical analysis
- Assistance to other developers and analysts
- Development of new features and bug fixes for WinSip ERP
- Definitions in meetings with sales, support, finance, commissions, operations and projects on scopes of changes and new developments
- A BI powered by information from this legacy ERP (SQL Server) was also developed, along with information from Salesforce, SAP Infoview and Elasticsearch that were imported via SSIS, for the dashboard, Power BI was used
- Technologies: SQL, Excel, Delphi 7, Delphi 2010, SQL Server, SQL Server Management Studio, SQL Server Integration Services (SSIS), Microsoft Power BI, Salesforce, SAP Infoview, Lucidchart, Elasticsearch, SoapUI

#### 2015 - 2015

# Systems Analyst (Juiz de Fora, MG - Brazil) – Guiando Telecom

- Thomson Reuters Outsourced
- Requirements analysis, technical analysis
- Development of new features and bug fixes in legacy ERP
- Technologies: SQL, Delphi 7, SQL Server, SQL Server Management Studio

## 2014 - 2014

#### Associate Delphi Developer (Juiz de Fora, MG - Brazil) – ProInfo

- Development of new features and bug fixes
- Technologies: SQL, Delphi 7, Firebird, IBExpert

# 2014 - 2014

# Associate Delphi Developer (Juiz de Fora, MG - Brazil) – Solucionar

• Development of new features and bug fixes

+55 (32) 9 9959-7577 | leandrodbahia@gmail.com

Technologies: SQL, Delphi 7, Oracle, Oracle SQL Developer

# 2011 - 2012

# Internship Delphi Developer (Juiz de Fora, MG - Brazil) – FG Digital Ltda ME

- Development of new features and bug fixes
- Technologies: SQL, Delphi 7, Firebird, Interbase, IBExpert

#### 2008 - 2010

# Internship Office Assistant (Juiz de Fora, MG - Brazil) – Goretti Irmãos Ltda

- Assist in the activities of office operation, document printing, filing, conference and launching of transport vouchers, filing and reception of employees
- Technologies: Word, Excel

#### COURSES

### 2024

## **Udemy**

#### 2023

• Snowflake [A-Z] Zero to Hero Masterclass (Core+SQL+API+Visual)

#### Coursera

Google Data Analytics Professional Certificate

# 2022

**Grupo Voitto** Storytelling fundamentals

# **EF Education First**

EF Standardized English Test: EF SET Certificate: 64/100, C1 Advanced

#### Alura

- Linux I: Knowing and Using the Terminal
- Linux II: programs, processes and packages
- Python: starting with the language
- Python: Advancing the Language
- Data Engineering: Getting to Know Apache Airflow
- Apache Beam: Data Pipeline with Python
- PostgreSQL
- PostgreSQL: Views, Sub-Queries, and Functions
- Data Engineering: Organizing Data on AWS
- Google Data Studio: Exploring Tool
- Google Data Studio: Accessing MySQL
- Google Data Studio: Filters and Functions
- Google Data Studio: Parameters and Big Query
- BigQuery: Google's Database for Big Data
- BigQuery: BigQuery functions
- BigQuery: Data Manipulation
- Big Query access: programmatic manipulation languages
- Google BigQuery and Data Studio: Final Project
- Relational Database Modeling: Entities, Relationships, and Attributes
- Relational Database Modeling: Model and Relational Algebra
- Relational Database Modeling: ER Diagram and Relational Model
- Relational Database Modeling: Normalization
- Relational Database Modeling: Understanding SQL
- Database Modeling: Getting Started with NoSQL
- Power BI Desktop: Building my first dashboard
- Dashboard with Power BI: Visualizing Data
- Power BI Desktop: Data handling in Power Query
- Power BI: Understanding DAX formulas

- Power BI: Exploring Visual Resources
- Business Intelligence: Introduction to Business Intelligence
- ETL with Integration Services: Data Model
- ETL with Integration Services: Data Transformation
- OLAP with SQL Server: Building the Data Warehouse
- Multidimensional Queries: MDX with SQL Server
- Report Analysis with Power BI: Generating Enterprise Reports
- ETL Models: Pentaho Data Integration
- Transformation with ETL: Pentaho Data Integration
- OLAP with Pentaho: Data Mart Construction
- Multidimensional Queries: MDX with Pentaho
- Report Analysis with Pentaho: Generating Enterprise Reports
- Dashboard with Pentaho: Visualize and analyze data

#### 2021 Alura

- SOLID with Java: Principles of Object Oriented Programming
- Java and DDD Introducing the concepts
- Introduction to SQL with Oracle: Manipulate and Query Data
- SQL Queries in Oracle: Projections, Selections, Joins and Views
- Data Manipulation in Oracle: DML Commands
- Oracle PL/SQL: Procedures, functions and exceptions
- Oracle PL/SQL: Mastering packages
- Oracle Database Administration: Database creation and management
- Oracle Database Administration: Bank Security and Optimization
- Oracle Database Performance: Environment Analysis
- Oracle Database Performance: Query Optimization
- Design Patterns in Java I: Introduction to good programming practices
- Design Patterns in Java II: Advancing in good programming practices
- TDD and Java: Automated Testing with Junit
- Integration Tests: Automated SQL Tests and DAOs in Java
- Selenium: Automated acceptance tests in Java
- BDD and Java: Behavior Driven Development with Cucumber
- Java and Clean Architecture: Uncomplicating software architecture
- Java and Domain Driven Design: Introducing the concepts

#### 2020 Cel.Lep

UI/UX Basics Skills

# IGTI

Salesforce Developer

# Cisco Networking Academy

CyberSecurity Essentials

#### Estácio de Sá 2018

Google Cloud

#### 2017 **Harvard Managementor**

- Manage your boss
- Career management
- Stress management
- Persuade other people
- Work ethics

# Performace – Gestão de projetos

PDCA training

#### 2009 **SEST SENAT**

Basic training in administrative services

# **Programming**

- Advanced
  - o SQL (DDL, DML, DQL, DTL, DCL, OLTP)
  - Microsoft Excel (formulas, VBA)
  - Delphi (Object pascal)
- Intermediate
  - Microsoft Power BI (DAX, M)
  - Microsoft Power Apps
  - Salesforce (Apex)
- Basic (academic knowledge or occasional use)
  - o Azure
  - AWS (Amazon Web Services)
  - o GCP (Google Cloud Platform)
  - o Linux
  - NoSQL
  - Python
  - o Apache Airflow
  - o Apache Spark
  - o Google Data Studio
  - o Google Looker
  - o Google Big Query
  - o Java
  - Javascript

#### **Database**

- Advanced
  - Snowflake
  - o Oracle
  - PostgreSQL
  - SQL Server
  - MySQL
  - o Firebird
  - Interbase
  - SQLite

# **Tecnologies**

- Advanced
  - Microsft Excel
  - Google Sheets
  - o GIT
  - o SVN
  - o JIRA / Confluence
  - o DBT
  - o PDI (Pentaho Data Integration)
  - SSIS (SQL Server Integration Services)
  - o Postman (SOAP, REST, XML, JSON)
  - SoapUI (SOAP, XML)
  - o Jenkins
  - o XML
  - o JSON
  - o YAML

# **Methodologies**

- Scrum
- Kanbam